CURRICULUM VITAE

LIMBUA MERCY MUTHONI

PO BOX 210-60602 KIANJAI-MERU

TEL: +254716553786/ +254731276956

EMAIL: <u>muthonilimbua@gmail.com</u>

PERSONAL INFORMATION

GENDER: FEMALE

NATIONALITY: KENYAN

MARITAL STATUS: SINGLE

LANGUAGES: ENGLISH, KISWAHILI

PROFILE SUMMARY

I am a passionate food scientist and technologist graduate from Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology. I have exemplary experience in the food and agribusiness industry space in particular implementation of codes of practices addressing food safety, designing and implementing agribusiness programs and projects, implementing programs addressing Food Nutrition and Security. I seek to participate in agribusiness and food industry development through implementation of food safety standards, policies, codes of practices and knowledge, and contribute to the attainment of Food Nutrition and. I am well versed with skills and knowledge on various standards e.g., Global Gap, GAPs, KS 1758 with extensive knowledge on climate smart agriculture (CSA), HACCP implementation; ISO 22000 and food safety management systems.

COMPETENCIES

- Knowledge in S.O.P, HACCP, Traceability System development.
- Knowledge in food and agriculture policies and standards (Global Gap, BRC Standards, FSMS, KS1758, BAPs)
- Ability to train in Food Safety; BAPS; KS1758; HACCP, Traceability
- Knowledgeable with Kenya's Agribusiness/ Agriculture industry with particular focused on horticulture, aquaculture and dairy.
- Very good written and verbal communication skills

• Ability to maintain confidentiality.

EDUCATION BACKGROUND

Jomo Kenyatta University of Agriculture and Technology September 2013 –June 2017

BSc. Food Science and Technology

Kianjai youth polytechnic

September-October 2013

Computer systems and applications

Matungulu Girls Secondary School (2010-2012)

Kenya certificate of secondary education, C+

Wankan Academy (2005-2008)

Kenya Certificate of Primary Education, 372(B+)

TRAININGS AND WORKSHOPS ATTENDED.

- Attended scaling up nutrition national symposium.
 Presented abstract on food safety and quality.
 November 23rd -24th 2016
 Awarded certificate of participation.
- Attended Kenya Standard (KS) 1758 trainer of trainees training July 1st -5th 2019
 Awarded certificate of trainer of trainees.
- Attended HighField Level 3 Trainers Training August 19th-23rd 2019
 Level 3 Trainer certified.
- Attended Food Safety Champion Course November 11-12th 2019
 Awarded certificate of Participation

WORKING EXPERIENCE

February 2018- date

Advocacy for Food Safety and Food Security in Kenya and Africa. (Twitter campaign @Limbua_mercy#IsupportSDG2)

- I engage in advocating for food safety and food security in Kenya and Africa and I majorly focused on: -
 - Pushing for adoption of safe food production practices by all food producers (farm- fork).
 - Sensitizing the public, government officials, industry players, policy makers and regulators
 on why food safety is a key element for the food security agenda and the general public
 health.
 - Sensitizing the public, government officials, industry players on reducing post-harvest losses towards achieving food security.

Pushing for adoption and implementation of food safety policies and regulations by the industry players and government officials.

May 2019- Date

Agroguild Consultancy- Team Lead

Food safety and value chain consultant offering: -

- Food safety, hygiene and sanitation trainings.
- Standard Operations Procedure Development.
- Kenya Standard 1758 training
- Food safety management system development
- Value addition training on fresh fruits and vegetables, dairy products.
- Good Agricultural Practices trainings.

May 2021-June 2021

Trade Mark East Africa- Consultant

Tasks undertaken and successful completed:

• Developed Food Safety Manual for horticulture and aquaculture industry.

- Developed training guides for: Horticulture, Dairy, Aquaculture
- Trained trainers of trainees along aquaculture value chain.

August 2020-March 2021

Invest in Africa-Agribusiness Project Lead

Responsibilities:

- Championing the growth of IIA's Wakulima Hub through identification, engagement and recruitment of Lead farmers, Youth and Women -Led groups, Aggregators to support the goals of the program.
- Ensuring registered farmers are trained on good agricultural practices on oil seed and beekeeping value chain.
- Designing of the Agribusiness Program.
- Supports and generation of internal and external project report.
- Supports liaison and engagement with key Partners, Collaborators and Counties to enhance and maintain the effective relationships and partner good will.
- Coordination of relevant meetings and working groups, maintains communication and tracks actions.
- Development and maintenance of databases of key market actors be used to further the projects objectives, linking these to off takers, financiers and input suppliers.

Key Achievement

- Redesigned the organization Wakulima hub portal.
- Mapped and defined value chains and programs of focused for IIA's Food and Agriculture work.

October 2019- June 2020

Asia Society for Social Improvement and Sustainable Transformation (ASSIT) - Consultant

Tasked undertaken and successful completed:

- Developed Aquaculture Standard Operating Procedure for TVET Kenya's curriculum.
- Provided Technical Support to the Somali Fish Inspection and Quality Assurance (FIQA) RTI project.

October 2019

Mugie Conservancy Ranch-Consultant

I trained and monitored staff on hygiene and sanitation, food handling, standard operating procedures and good slaughtering practices.

February 2018 –November 2018

Ecosystem Based Adaption for Food Security Assembly (EBAFOSA)-Innovative volunteer

-Under the EBAFOSA pillar one: -Amalgamation of clean energy development to add value to EBA-driven agriculture to maximize productivity.

Responsibilities: -

- On-farm: Key interventions are in mapping out irrigation (solar powered, microirrigation), basic value chain addition e.g., drying (solar driers), other preservation (solar fridges), storage (solar powered silos)
- Post-farm gate: Mapping out solar micro-grids/decentralized power systems that can power a processing factory.
- Mapping relevant energy initiatives/ enterprises that can supply appropriate technology and technical expertise to power various levels of agro-value addition.
- Linking the energy enterprises to farmers when demand arises.

February 2018 to July 2018

Society of Crop Agribusiness Advisory of Kenya (SOCAA)-intern

Responsibilities: -

- Reviewing and reporting on food safety technical assignments, subjects and topics and presenting reports.
- Reviewing of county integrated development scheme (CIDPS) projects on food safety and security.
- Representing SOCAA in meetings addressing food safety and security and giving reports.
- Assisting with planning, monitory and evaluation of the organization activities.
- Assisting in the development of the organization working plan towards addressing food safety.
- Updating the CSO log book.

August 2017 to January 2018

Nairobi Airport Services (NAS) – Food Microbiology & Quality Assurance (Intern).

Hygiene and food safety department

- Responsible for ensuring adherence to specifications and quality procedures in accordance with hazard analysis and critical control point (HACCP) and ISO 22000 standards.
- Conduct follow-ups on corrective actions taken.
- Maintain compliance with specific QC/QA standards and GMPs in production area
- Ensure Kaizen practice designated initiatives are implemented in the department leading to continual productivity.
- Ensure that the staffs in the production areas are supplied with appropriate clothing such as face masks and disposable gloves.
- Training new staffs on basic hygiene and sanitation.
- Inspection of in-bound materials at receiving area of main stores.

Food microbiology laboratory

- Laboratory analysis in accordance with ISO 17025 standards, general requirements for the competence of testing and calibration laboratories as set by (ISO).
- Responsible for carrying out water and food analysis
- Collecting food samples for analysis before and after production.

May 2016 - August 2016

Coffee Research Institute- Quality Control (Attaché)

Responsibilities: -

- Coffee analysis that includes analysis of caffeine, sugar, mycotoxins.
- Coffee bean roasting.
- I was also exposed to the knowledge of primary coffee processing.

May 2015 - June 2015

Jomo Kenyatta university of Agriculture and Technology-Food science production Workshop (Attaché)

Responsibilities: -

- I got the exposure to the production of meat products, dairy products, fruits juices and jams and baked products.
- I was also exposed to the knowledge of chemical, microbial analysis of the food products and quality determination

ASSOCIATIONS

- Fresh Produce Consortium of Kenya- Member
- OFAB Kenya Associate Program 2020/2021

CERTIFICATIONS

Kenya Standard 1758:2 Trainer of Trainees

Food safety Champion- level 1

High field level 3 trainer

ACHIEVEMENTS

- 1. Successfully developed aquaculture standard operating procedures that has been accepted for used in Kenya's TVET curriculum.
- 2. Successfully developed food safety manual for horticulture and aquaculture in for used in enhancing food safety across the value chains in respect to covid 19.
- 3. Successfully developed food safety training guides for aquaculture, horticulture, dairy for used by Trainers of Trainees in capacity building value chain players in enhancing their food safety practices.

HOBBIES AND INTERESTS

Swimming, charity work, reading novels, writing and reading articles, research, team-building, cycling

REFEREES

1.MARK NZOMO MICROBILOGIST NAIROBI AIRPORT SERVICES P.O.BOX 19010-00100 NAIROBI

TEL: 0722763111

mark.nzomo@servair.co.ke

2.DR. ANDREW EDEWA
DIRECTOR STANDARDS & SPS MEASURES
TRADE MARK EAST AFRICA
P.O.BOX 313-00606
NAIROBI

Tel: 07204235000

andrew.edewa@trademarkea.com

3.PHILIP CHEMELTORIT CHIEF INSPECTOR KEPHIS P.O.BOX 1679-20100 NAKURU

Tel: 0721250247

pchemeltorit@kephis.org